Guide to the Keep America Out of War Congress Records TAM.331
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Keep America Out of War Congress Records, 1936-1946
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dodge, Alice L.
Keep America Out of War Congress
TAM.331
1.5 Linear Feet In 1 record carton and 2 oversize flat boxes.
Initiated in March of 1938, the Keep America Out of War Congress was a pacifist-socialist coalition whose goal was to preserve and strengthen the anti-war movement. After the attack on Pearl Harbor in December 1941, the group dissolved and briefly became the Provisional Committee Toward a Democratic Peace. In early 1942 it was reorganized into the Post War World Council. This collection contains membership cards and mailing lists, correspondence, meeting minutes, topical files on various pertinent subjects, receipt books and a number of pamphlets published by the organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Alice Dodge Wolfson in 2001. The accession number associated with this gift is 2001.207.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within one series:
Missing Title
Series I: Keep America Out of War Congress and Subsequent Organizations, 1936-1946.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Keep America Out of War Congress (KAOWC) was officially founded at a rally held on March 6, 1938, in the New York Hippodrome. The host and sponsor was the Socialist Party, and the chairman, veteran pacifist reformer Oswald Garrison Villard. Speakers included Robert M. LaFollette Jr., socialist leader Norman Thomas and columnist John T. Flynn. The national platform called for withdrawal from such 'imperialist' involvement as the stationing of American ships and marines in China's war zones; the scrapping of plans for industrial mobilization, conscription, and foreign alliances; the termination of war trade; and national adoption of a war referendum. The Congress created a skeletal organization (initially called the Keep America Out of War Committee), and made provision for state and local units.
For most of its life, the KAOWC was a coalition composed of the Socialist Party and six militant peace organizations: The Peace Section of the American Friends Service Committee; The Fellowship of Reconciliation; The World Peace Commission of the Methodist Church; The American Section of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; The National Council for the Prevention of War; and The War Resisters League.
One controversial aspect of the organization, given its liberal constituency, was its relationship with the America First Committee. While opposing America First's stress upon rearmament and its silence concerning conscription, the KAOWC still welcomed its formation, accepted significant donations and co-sponsored some New York rallies. When Charles A. Lindbergh, America First's most noted leader, gave a speech on September 11, 1941, claiming that 'Jewish groups' were among those agitating for war, the Congress governing committee strongly objected on the grounds that he was encouraging domestic intolerance.
In December of 1941, when the Japanese attacked Pearl Harbor, the KAOWC quickly dissolved. Property was turned over to a hastily formed body, the Provisional Committee Toward a Democratic Peace, which, in early 1942, became the Post War World Council. The new organization was created by Norman Thomas and his associates to work toward a democratic, non-imperialist peace settlement. Thomas was committed to developing plans for peace that would prevent all future wars, promoting international relations and universal disarmament in newsletters, editorials, press releases and letters to government officials and guiding the organization as it published pamphlets and organized conferences. Activities slowed down in 1965 because of his failing health. Some efforts, including a newsletter, continued until December 1967 when the organization was officially dissolved after Thomas suffered a severe stroke.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oral History of the American Left: Radical Histories Collection, Interviews with Alice Dodge Wolfson and Fay Bennet. (OH 002)
Daniel Bell Research Files on US Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement. (TAM 080)
Norman Thomas Papers (TAM 423)
Sources: The Swarthmore College Peace Collection holds records of both the Keep America Out of War Congress, 1938-1942 (Collection CDG-A) and the Post War World Council, 1942-1967 (Collection DG 062).
Scope and Content Note
The majority of items within this collection relate to the Keep America Out of War Congress. Included are a small amount of correspondence, minutes of several governing committee meetings and internal memoranda. There are two receipt books (October 1941 through February 1942) that reflect contributions, membership dues, and purchases of publications and event tickets. Many annotations have been made on the duplicate receipts. In addition, a card file contains member names and addresses, pledges, payment of dues, some descriptions of the individuals (e.g. job, age), comments about correspondence, special requests, event attendance and various other notations. Many topical files are included, touching on such subjects as "Anti-Nazi Activities and Unrest in Europe," "Labor and War," "Post War Problems," "Wiretapping," and "What War Would Do to America." The files contain articles, newspaper clippings, speeches, correspondence, press releases, newsletters, pamphlets, excerpts from The Congressional Record, bulletins and notes.
There is a relatively small amount of material associated with the Post War World Council, including correspondence, descriptive fliers and pamphlets on topics such as peacetime conscription, world federation, international cartels and world peace, disarmament and self-determination for Puerto Rico.
The items in this collection were accumulated by Alice L. Dodge (Wolfson) who served as the Organization Secretary for the Keep American Out of War Congress.
Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Membership lists.; Socialism -- United States.; Press releases.; Peace movements -- United States.; Correspondence.; Notes.; Clippings (information artifacts); World War, 1939-1945.; Brochures.; Circulars (fliers); Card files.; Bulletins.; Pacifists |z United States.; Dodge, Alice L.; Keep America Out of War Congress; America First Committee; Post War World Council; Provisional Committee Toward a Democratic Peace; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968
- Series I: Keep America Out of War Congress and Successor Organizations, 1936-1946.
  - Keep America Out of War Congress, 1939-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Card File - Members, Addresses, Dues and Contributions, Notes (I), 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Card File - Members, Addresses, Dues and Contributions, Notes (II), 1938-1941 (Box 3)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Duplicate Receipts, Oct 14, 1941 - Dec 3, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Duplicate Receipts ( Provisional Committee Toward a Democratic Peace begins at Jan 12, 1942), Dec 3, 1941 - Feb 25, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Anti-Labor Legislation, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Anti-Nazi Activities and Unrest in Europe, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Army Morale, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Britain and War, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Causes of Entry into Last War, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Eight Points, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Farmers, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Food for Europe, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Impossibility of Invasion, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - India, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Inflation, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Japan, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Labor and War, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Local Notes, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Negroes, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Neutrality Campaign, Ship Sinkings and Roosevelt's May Day Speech, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Organizational Suggestions and Actions, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Peace Offensive, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Post War Problems, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Priority Unemployment, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Roosevelt (FDR) Quotes, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Smear Campaign, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Social Security Revision, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Taxation, Profits and Cost of Living, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - US Raw Materials to the Axis, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Various Anti-War Items, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - War Aims, Britain During and After the War, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - War and Foreign Trade, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - War Economy and Armament Economics, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - What Does the Peace Movement Accomplish?, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - What War Would Do to America, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress: Subject Files - Wiretapping, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mailing Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Post War World Council, 1942-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Post War World Council: Peacetime Conscription, 1944-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Post War World Council: Pamphlets - Various Topics, 1942-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)